in a chemical reaction, the original substance(s) (aka reactants) change into new substances (aka products)
no new matter is created; all of the mass in reactants = mass of products
the atoms just rearrange in a chemical reaction

they can be written in 2 ways:
  a word equation: Nitrogen monoxide + oxygen --> nitrogen dioxide
  and symbolic: 2NO(g) + O₂(g) --> 2NO₂(g)
                ^                 ^
                |                 |
  +-------------+-----------------+
  |
coefficients: (big number in front of the compounds) indicate the ratio of compounds in the reaction (here, there is 2x NO as O)
