the law of conservation of mass is that in a chemical reaction, atoms are neither created or destroyed.
- mass of reactants are **ALWAYS** equal to mass of product(s)
- atoms are always conserved as well
- molecules may be changed


because of this, we can count atoms, and add them to balance the number of atoms in chemical equations

an example:

  word equation: Methane + Oxygen --> Water + Carbon Dioxide
  which is: CH₄(g) + O₂(g) --> H₂O(i) + CO₂(g)
  to ba;ance, look how many atoms are on each side of the reaction arrow

  1 C, 4 H, 2 O --> 1 C, 2 H, 3 O
  to balance, find values that equate atoms on both side
  
  1 C, 4 H, (2x2) O --> 1 C, (2x2) H, (2x1)+2 O
  CH₄(g) + 2O₂(g) --> 2H₂O(l) + CO₂(g)
  