in order for a reaction to occur, the particles of the reactants must collide, which means the bonds will break, and new bonds will form.
wether the reaction actually happens depends on wether or not they have enough kinetic energy to break bonds, and the position of the collision.
each chemical reaction has a minimum amount of energy required for it to occur, as it needs enough energy to break the bonds, and rearrange themselves into new particles.
bonds within a compound are a source of potential energy, as it requires some energy to set it off, and then releases energy.

if more energy is released during the reaction than it takes to set it off, than it is called exothermic, if less is released than required, than it is endothermic.


ENDOTHERMIC REACTIONS:
will be cold
a reaction is endothermic when the bond breaking process in the reactnats requires more energy than is released.
in an endothermic reaction the products have more energy than the reactants did because energy was absorbed during the reaction.
photosynthesis is an endothermic reaction, as it is using the suns energy to turn carbon dioxide and water into glucose and oxygen.

EXOTHERMIC REACTIONS:
will be hot
these reactions release energy. the energy from chemical reactions is measured in kilojoules (kj).
say we had a reaction like this:
X₂ + Y₂ --> 2xy
50 kj is required to break the bonds that hold the x's and y's together, but 100 kj is released when xy forms. you would write this like:
50 kj + x₂ + y₂ --> 2xy + 100 kj
since it is an equation, you can simplify it:
x₂ + y₂ --> 2xy + 50 kj
which shows that 50 kj are being released
it's good to use ΔH notation, that is, once the reaction is written, followed by a negative value for ΔH that shows the change in heat:
x₂ + y₂ --> 2xy, ΔH= -50 kj
cellular respiration is an exothermic reaction; burning glucose to produce energy. oxygen is also required, from the air.
