Metal oxides will react with water, and form bases.
Na₂O(s) + H₂O(l) --> 2NaOH(aq)

Non-metal oxides will react with water to form acids
So₂(g) + H₂O(l) --> H₂SO₃(aq)
non-metal oxides are formed when burning fossil fuels, and are introduced into the atmosphere. this causes acid rain.

Acids react with metals. the metals in groups 2 and 1 (alkali and alkaline earth metals) react with acids vigourously. H₂(g) is released when acids react with metals.

Carbonates (-CO₃) will neutralize acids and release carbon dioxide gas (CO₂), and thats basically all there is to say.
