salts are ionic compounds, and they are formed when acids and bases react. they are always made of a positive ion from a base and a negative ion from an acid.
they are found in many things, such as batteries, explosives, multivitamins, and many living cells.

neutralization:
 neutralization is how salts are formed, when a base and an acid react. 

acid + base --> salt + water

eg.
 HCL(aq) + NaOH(aq)--> NaCl(s) + H₂O(l)
 Lye + Hydrochloric acid --> table salt + water

