A single replacement is when one element from a compound is replaced with a seperate element, which is added as a reactant.

A + BC --> B + AC  where A is a metal, or
A + BC --> C + BA  where A is a non-metal

aluminum foil in copper chloride will produce solid copper and aluminum chloride; 2 Al + 3 CuCl₂ --> 3 Cu + 2 AlCl₃
(example of single replacement where A is a metal(Al))

flourine put through a sodium iodine solution will produce iodine and sodium flouride; F₂ +  2 NaI --> I₂ + 2 NaF